<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-12-11T13:50:03+06:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/</id><title type="html">Your awesome title</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Story 6</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story_6.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Story 6" /><published>2017-12-10T00:00:00+06:00</published><updated>2017-12-10T00:00:00+06:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story_6</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story_6.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The case for Yes&lt;/strong&gt;
Consider the count: two finance ministers down.
One of them, Pravin Gordhan, has put the cost of state capture at R100-billion while there is evidence of billions of rands leaving the country illegally.
Important institutions are in shambles. At least one motivation for the capture of the SA Revenue Service was because its former executives had opened files on the splurge at the president’s private residence in Nkandla and because it had started investigating the Gupta family.
A Swiss-based shell company that hawks &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/sunday-times/business/2017-08-24-guptas-bail-out-of-another-sa-business/&quot;&gt;a gaudy clothing range now owns Tegeta&lt;/a&gt;, a prime South African coal asset.
From small-time IT people, the Gupta family are now a multinational oligarchy courtesy of South African citizens and taxpayers. Some of that fortune can be attributed to the creation of a false narrative. But what the Guptas’ multimillion-rand spin campaign successfully did was conflate the fight for economic justice with its own campaign to accumulate wealth.
The measure of South Africa’s inequality, the Gini coefficient, is inching down too slowly and business has not sufficiently transformed to represent the country in which it operates. On behalf of the Guptas, Bell Pottinger used this fact to create the smokescreen of “white monopoly capital” to legitimise their looting spree.
The UK PR company’s sales pitch is that its campaigns can influence policy. The ANCIR study shows that while a lot of the fake news was easily routed out as rubbish, the messages of the dominance of white monopoly capital was influential.
&lt;strong&gt;The case for No&lt;/strong&gt;
It failed miserably. South African internet sleuths took about three months in the second half of 2016 to begin uncovering the fake news narrative.
Once the robot was discovered, it was simple to spot the fakes because their creators were sloppy. The campaign became a national joke and a massive waste of money for the Guptas. Bell Pottinger thought it could come to South Africa to engage in the same dark spin operations that gained it notoriety in many regimes including Iraq.
Instead, South Africa’s activist spirit has put the company on the defensive and split it down the middle. The anti fake news Twitter community trolled Bell Pottinger so persistently that it locked down its feed and later &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/sunday-times/opinion-and-analysis/2017-08-02-fact-vs-fiction-how-bell-pottinger-and-atul-gupta-spun-the-bbc/&quot;&gt;apologised for the South African campaign&lt;/a&gt;. It fired the lead manager on the Gupta account, Victoria Geoghegan.
The firm’s founder, Tim Bell, has said publicly that he warned against taking on the account. CEO James Henderson resigned over the weekend before the publication of the findings of an inquiry by a law firm Bell Pottinger hired to examine the Gupta affair.
For the first time in its history, Bell Pottinger has been called to account for its work by the UK PR industry standards body.
And, back home, the Gupta family are being squeezed out of the economy by the banking sector which has fired them as clients.
This story was published in partnership with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/news/south-africa/2017-09-04-analysis--so-did-the-gupta-familys-fake-news-campaign-work/&quot;&gt;The Times.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Test" /><category term="Ipsum" /><category term="Markdown" /><category term="Portfolio" /><summary type="html">The case for Yes Consider the count: two finance ministers down. One of them, Pravin Gordhan, has put the cost of state capture at R100-billion while there is evidence of billions of rands leaving the country illegally. Important institutions are in shambles. At least one motivation for the capture of the SA Revenue Service was because its former executives had opened files on the splurge at the president’s private residence in Nkandla and because it had started investigating the Gupta family. A Swiss-based shell company that hawks a gaudy clothing range now owns Tegeta, a prime South African coal asset. From small-time IT people, the Gupta family are now a multinational oligarchy courtesy of South African citizens and taxpayers. Some of that fortune can be attributed to the creation of a false narrative. But what the Guptas’ multimillion-rand spin campaign successfully did was conflate the fight for economic justice with its own campaign to accumulate wealth. The measure of South Africa’s inequality, the Gini coefficient, is inching down too slowly and business has not sufficiently transformed to represent the country in which it operates. On behalf of the Guptas, Bell Pottinger used this fact to create the smokescreen of “white monopoly capital” to legitimise their looting spree. The UK PR company’s sales pitch is that its campaigns can influence policy. The ANCIR study shows that while a lot of the fake news was easily routed out as rubbish, the messages of the dominance of white monopoly capital was influential. The case for No It failed miserably. South African internet sleuths took about three months in the second half of 2016 to begin uncovering the fake news narrative. Once the robot was discovered, it was simple to spot the fakes because their creators were sloppy. The campaign became a national joke and a massive waste of money for the Guptas. Bell Pottinger thought it could come to South Africa to engage in the same dark spin operations that gained it notoriety in many regimes including Iraq. Instead, South Africa’s activist spirit has put the company on the defensive and split it down the middle. The anti fake news Twitter community trolled Bell Pottinger so persistently that it locked down its feed and later apologised for the South African campaign. It fired the lead manager on the Gupta account, Victoria Geoghegan. The firm’s founder, Tim Bell, has said publicly that he warned against taking on the account. CEO James Henderson resigned over the weekend before the publication of the findings of an inquiry by a law firm Bell Pottinger hired to examine the Gupta affair. For the first time in its history, Bell Pottinger has been called to account for its work by the UK PR industry standards body. And, back home, the Gupta family are being squeezed out of the economy by the banking sector which has fired them as clients. This story was published in partnership with The Times.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/img/blog/Thumb-6.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Story 5</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story_5.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Story 5" /><published>2017-12-10T00:00:00+06:00</published><updated>2017-12-10T00:00:00+06:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story_5</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story_5.html">&lt;p&gt;How fake messages from the black-ops world of an automated Twitter army spilled over into reality
At the end of August, an increasingly desperate Gupta family sold their media assets to former government bureaucrat and Tiger Brands executive &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/sunday-times/news/2017-08-26-i-know-what-ive-signed-up-for-manyi-spills-the-beans-on-his-new-business/&quot;&gt;Mzwanele “Jimmy” Manyi&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/sunday-times/business/2017-08-22-manyi-overpaid-guptas-for-ann7-and-the-new-age-valuation-shows/&quot;&gt;The R450-million valuation of the New Age and ANN7&lt;/a&gt; has come in for sharp corporate scrutiny but the sale reveals why Manyi is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/news/south-africa/2017-09-01-defamatory-posts-by-manyi-scare-billionaire/&quot;&gt;significant influencer&lt;/a&gt; in the fake news campaign.
His is one of 19 authentic accounts that took the message from the black-ops world of an automated Twitter army into the networks of power in the real world.
The Black First Land First (BLF) movement and its founder, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/politics/2017-08-08-blf-mngxitama-in-contempt-of-court-for-harassing-journalists/&quot;&gt;Andile Mngxitama&lt;/a&gt;, are also commanders of the fake news army. Mngxitama was funded by the Gupta family and is a regular commentator on ANN7.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/news/south-africa/2017-08-25-the-bell-begins-to-toll-guptas-uk-spin-doctors-in-breach/&quot;&gt;Bell Pottinger’s role&lt;/a&gt; in creating the fake Twitter and Facebook army will only emerge once the company reveals the results of an internal investigation.
But the UK PR company was central to the attempt to shift the debate away from state capture by President Jacob Zuma and his collaborators towards the purported dominance of the economy by white-owned or controlled businesses.
A range of hashtags was coined to coincide with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/politics/2017-07-14-gordhan-rejects-apology-calls-it-a-pathetic-cover-up/&quot;&gt;political campaign to change the leadership of the Treasury&lt;/a&gt; and the South African Reserve Bank; to put pressure on banks to re-open the Guptas’ accounts; and to ensure that former public protector Thuli Madonsela’s State of Capture report reached a dead end.
The #PravinMustGo hashtag was retweeted 24,463 times while former finance minister Pravin Gordhan had another 8,936 tweets authored about him. (A separate analysis puts the number much higher at 183,620 tweets from 32,180 users.)
The campaign to discount state capture and as Madonsela’s report used another 18,000 tweets. Former deputy finance minister Mcebisi Jonas, who turned down a R600-million bribe to be Gordhan’s successor, faced a barrage of 3,500 negative tweets.
At least 15 journalists who wrote about state capture were lampooned in graphics as lapdogs of white monopoly capital under the hashtag #mediacapture via 3,418 tweets.
Like the Infogate campaign of the 1970s, this new version had specific political purposes. Topics related to the National Treasury and the Reserve Bank were tweeted 41,515 times and the campaign against white monopoly capital got 10,810 tweets.
This analysis shows that the network’s primary goal was to capture the National Treasury and the Reserve Bank. Aside from this objective, significant energy was focused on setting up “white monopoly capital” as the enemy, rather than state capture, and on attacking critics of the Gupta empire and President Zuma.
&lt;strong&gt;No comment&lt;/strong&gt;
Bell Pottinger did not respond to requests for comments.
The Gupta family, via its spokesperson Gary Naidoo, did not respond to calls and emails requesting comment.
New media magnate Manyi said his positions on all the topics raised in the misinformation campaign predated it.
In his work at the Black Management Forum, the Progressive Professionals Forum and the Decolonisation Foundation, he had been at the front of the push for corporate transformation.
He disputed that Bell Pottinger or the Gupta family had coined the term “white monopoly capital” or the campaign behind it. He also said Finance Minister Malusi Gigaba’s advisor Chris Malikane has shown this form of capital being identified as a cause of South Africa’s problems since 1962.
“My Twitter handle reflects genuine issues and if they overlap with other agendas, I have no control over that,” said Manyi.
Mngxitama of the BLF said: “I’ve got 70,000 followers and I follow 1,000 accounts. I can’t authenticate all of them. It’s a virtual world.”
Asked if his organisation and its websites were funded by the Gupta family, he laughed.  “I would really love to get the Gupta money. I must write an open letter to Atul [Gupta].”
This story was published in partnership with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/news/south-africa/2017-09-04-meet-the-real-life-commanders-of-the-guptas-fake-news-army/&quot;&gt;The Times.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Test" /><category term="Ipsum" /><category term="Markdown" /><category term="Portfolio" /><summary type="html">How fake messages from the black-ops world of an automated Twitter army spilled over into reality At the end of August, an increasingly desperate Gupta family sold their media assets to former government bureaucrat and Tiger Brands executive Mzwanele “Jimmy” Manyi. The R450-million valuation of the New Age and ANN7 has come in for sharp corporate scrutiny but the sale reveals why Manyi is a significant influencer in the fake news campaign. His is one of 19 authentic accounts that took the message from the black-ops world of an automated Twitter army into the networks of power in the real world. The Black First Land First (BLF) movement and its founder, Andile Mngxitama, are also commanders of the fake news army. Mngxitama was funded by the Gupta family and is a regular commentator on ANN7. Bell Pottinger’s role in creating the fake Twitter and Facebook army will only emerge once the company reveals the results of an internal investigation. But the UK PR company was central to the attempt to shift the debate away from state capture by President Jacob Zuma and his collaborators towards the purported dominance of the economy by white-owned or controlled businesses. A range of hashtags was coined to coincide with a political campaign to change the leadership of the Treasury and the South African Reserve Bank; to put pressure on banks to re-open the Guptas’ accounts; and to ensure that former public protector Thuli Madonsela’s State of Capture report reached a dead end. The #PravinMustGo hashtag was retweeted 24,463 times while former finance minister Pravin Gordhan had another 8,936 tweets authored about him. (A separate analysis puts the number much higher at 183,620 tweets from 32,180 users.) The campaign to discount state capture and as Madonsela’s report used another 18,000 tweets. Former deputy finance minister Mcebisi Jonas, who turned down a R600-million bribe to be Gordhan’s successor, faced a barrage of 3,500 negative tweets. At least 15 journalists who wrote about state capture were lampooned in graphics as lapdogs of white monopoly capital under the hashtag #mediacapture via 3,418 tweets. Like the Infogate campaign of the 1970s, this new version had specific political purposes. Topics related to the National Treasury and the Reserve Bank were tweeted 41,515 times and the campaign against white monopoly capital got 10,810 tweets. This analysis shows that the network’s primary goal was to capture the National Treasury and the Reserve Bank. Aside from this objective, significant energy was focused on setting up “white monopoly capital” as the enemy, rather than state capture, and on attacking critics of the Gupta empire and President Zuma. No comment Bell Pottinger did not respond to requests for comments. The Gupta family, via its spokesperson Gary Naidoo, did not respond to calls and emails requesting comment. New media magnate Manyi said his positions on all the topics raised in the misinformation campaign predated it. In his work at the Black Management Forum, the Progressive Professionals Forum and the Decolonisation Foundation, he had been at the front of the push for corporate transformation. He disputed that Bell Pottinger or the Gupta family had coined the term “white monopoly capital” or the campaign behind it. He also said Finance Minister Malusi Gigaba’s advisor Chris Malikane has shown this form of capital being identified as a cause of South Africa’s problems since 1962. “My Twitter handle reflects genuine issues and if they overlap with other agendas, I have no control over that,” said Manyi. Mngxitama of the BLF said: “I’ve got 70,000 followers and I follow 1,000 accounts. I can’t authenticate all of them. It’s a virtual world.” Asked if his organisation and its websites were funded by the Gupta family, he laughed. “I would really love to get the Gupta money. I must write an open letter to Atul [Gupta].” This story was published in partnership with The Times.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/img/blog/Thumb-5.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Story 4</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story_4.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Story 4" /><published>2017-12-10T00:00:00+06:00</published><updated>2017-12-10T00:00:00+06:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story_4</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story_4.html">&lt;p&gt;The Gupta campaign used social media as a weapon to target key opponents and replicated methods successfully used elsewhere in the world.
The network of websites, as well as The New Age and ANN7, hosted the main narratives of the campaign, which sought to deflect attention from the Guptas’ looting to the racial ownership of the South African economy.
The chosen fall guy for the campaign was the billionaire Johann Rupert, who cancelled his luxury goods company’s massive retainer with Bell Pottinger as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/sunday-times/opinion-and-analysis/2017-07-15-bell-pottinger-tapped---a-potent-struggle-allegory/&quot;&gt;fake news war gained ground&lt;/a&gt;.
The campaign included political targets such as former finance minister Pravin Gordhan and the National Treasury as well as the South African Reserve Bank — the supposed roadblocks in the path of the Gupta juggernaut.
The main focus was Twitter, the micro-blogging site that has 7.7-million users in South Africa. The propagandists also used Google Ads, Facebook Ads and possibly Twitter Ads to spread their messaging.
The participants in the fake news empire spread 220,431 tweets between July 2016 and July 2017. They authored 4,849 tweets which were retweeted 215,582 times by the automated arm of the campaign.
On Facebook, 3,574 posts were made which attracted 6,713 comments and 28,121 likes. The posts were shared 8,256 times. This kind of online virality spreads fake news and gives it impact. It is widely believed to be behind the success of the election of US President Donald Trump.
Two types of fake accounts were used.
Firstly, accounts were created manually and then orchestrated as a collective “botnet” – an automated robotic network.
The second type of accounts, which emerged after the #GuptaEmails were exposed, appear to have been hired via the international black market. They contain features indicative of fake accounts for hire — which often come with provenance in the form of a long-standing presence on Twitter, giving them face-value legitimacy in the eyes of the average user.
The fake twitter army worked with generals and foot-soldiers: the primary fake accounts published links to the network’s websites and other media outlets while the foot-soldier accounts amplified the message by re-tweeting the primary accounts.
This story was published in partnership with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/news/south-africa/2017-09-04-how-the-gupta-campaign-weaponised-social-media/&quot;&gt;The Times.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Test" /><category term="Ipsum" /><category term="Markdown" /><category term="Portfolio" /><summary type="html">The Gupta campaign used social media as a weapon to target key opponents and replicated methods successfully used elsewhere in the world. The network of websites, as well as The New Age and ANN7, hosted the main narratives of the campaign, which sought to deflect attention from the Guptas’ looting to the racial ownership of the South African economy. The chosen fall guy for the campaign was the billionaire Johann Rupert, who cancelled his luxury goods company’s massive retainer with Bell Pottinger as the fake news war gained ground. The campaign included political targets such as former finance minister Pravin Gordhan and the National Treasury as well as the South African Reserve Bank — the supposed roadblocks in the path of the Gupta juggernaut. The main focus was Twitter, the micro-blogging site that has 7.7-million users in South Africa. The propagandists also used Google Ads, Facebook Ads and possibly Twitter Ads to spread their messaging. The participants in the fake news empire spread 220,431 tweets between July 2016 and July 2017. They authored 4,849 tweets which were retweeted 215,582 times by the automated arm of the campaign. On Facebook, 3,574 posts were made which attracted 6,713 comments and 28,121 likes. The posts were shared 8,256 times. This kind of online virality spreads fake news and gives it impact. It is widely believed to be behind the success of the election of US President Donald Trump. Two types of fake accounts were used. Firstly, accounts were created manually and then orchestrated as a collective “botnet” – an automated robotic network. The second type of accounts, which emerged after the #GuptaEmails were exposed, appear to have been hired via the international black market. They contain features indicative of fake accounts for hire — which often come with provenance in the form of a long-standing presence on Twitter, giving them face-value legitimacy in the eyes of the average user. The fake twitter army worked with generals and foot-soldiers: the primary fake accounts published links to the network’s websites and other media outlets while the foot-soldier accounts amplified the message by re-tweeting the primary accounts. This story was published in partnership with The Times.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/img/blog/Thumb-4.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Story 3</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story_3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Story 3" /><published>2017-12-10T00:00:00+06:00</published><updated>2017-12-10T00:00:00+06:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story_3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story_3.html">&lt;p&gt;
  The Gupta family’s propaganda campaign, allegedly assisted by Bell Pottinger, inaugurated South Africa into the epicentre of the era of fake news and propaganda which has grown in tandem with the dominance of news by social media platforms.
  How does it work?
  A report by cybersecurity firm Trend Micro, &lt;a href=&quot;https://documents.trendmicro.com/assets/white_papers/wp-fake-news-machine-how-propagandists-abuse-the-internet.pdf&quot;&gt;“The Fake News Machine: How Propagandists Abuse the Internet and Manipulate the Public”&lt;/a&gt;, details how to set up or procure a group capable of employing “dark” means to amplify content online. These services are mostly found on the “darknet” (part of the internet infamous for the trade in illegal drugs, child porn and other illegal services).
  On the darknet, technology propagandists claim they can artificially manipulate a wide variety of online platforms including Facebook, Twitter, YouTube and Instagram.
  They offer services such as:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;On Twitter: creating accounts, buying followers and creating retweets;&lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;On Facebook: creating accounts, buying followers, comments and “likes”;&lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;On YouTube: buying “likes”, “dislikes”, views, video reviews and making videos appear on the front page;&lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;Using “click farms”, software and hardware for automating activities such as liking and following, and;&lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;News manipulation: for example, writing press releases and guaranteed article placements on news sites (especially in Russia and China).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Trend Micro’s researchers identify distinct regions where prominent marketplaces exist, each with their own culture, tools and platform priorities. These are China, the Middle East, India and English-speaking communities.
  The Russian community has a particular focus on using real humans to complete tasks through crowdsourcing platforms. Some of these darknet platforms to manipulate social media are very large. Vtope reportedly has two million “mostly real” users and SMOFast has roughly 500,000 registered users.
  There is evidence that suggests that India, along with Bell Pottinger in the UK, were part of a multinational campaign of fake news sponsored by the Gupta family.
  Internet sleuth Jean le Roux has followed the bot army for months. He first revealed its existence in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dailymaverick.co.za/article/2017-06-22-scorpio-in-the-non-surprise-of-the-year-wmcleaks.com-smear-campaign-tracked-to-a-gupta-associate/&quot;&gt;Daily Maverick&lt;/a&gt; when he showed how a sample of fake accounts was spreading the propaganda at exactly the same time, which indicated an automated campaign.
  In other words, the accounts did not act as individual humans but as a trolling battalion acting for a political purpose. “It’s definitely multinational,” says Le Roux, who would send some of the accounts links. When those behind the accounts opened the links, it revealed to Le Roux that the accounts were generated from both South Africa and India.
  The campaigners used rupee (the Indian currency) to use Google Ads or promoted tweets to increase the visibility of their messages. Some of the fake accounts were linked to documents that were often geo-located in India.
  In other words, the Gupta family’s Twitter army left a digital footprint.
  In addition, says Le Roux, his suspicions were piqued when the accounts carried names like Bongi Vorster and Dlamini Louw. While African-Afrikaans name and surname combinations are known, they are rare — but were very common in the fake army.
  “It was as if someone had been given a spreadsheet of South African names and surnames which were then automatically generating combinations,” he says.
  Then Le Roux sent the fake accounts messages in several South African languages other than English, and they couldn’t answer.
  All this indicated a paid foreign army with its base probably in India.
  While there is no direct evidence of Bell Pottinger’s role in this part of the campaign, the company has a long history of propaganda black operations. These “black ops” hide the creators of work that is designed to confuse and destabilise countries. The PR company has most recently been exposed for its work in Iraq where it created videos and other material to smoke out alleged Al-Qaeda operatives.
  Wikipedia founder Jimmy Wales banned Bell Pottinger from editing on the open online encyclopaedia after it was found to have manipulated various entries.
  The Bell Pottinger team that worked on South Africa also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/politics/2017-07-10-bell-pottingers-wicked-wiki-ways/&quot;&gt;sanitised the Gupta family’s Wikipedia entry&lt;/a&gt;, as The Times has previously shown.
  This story was published in partnership with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/news/south-africa/2017-09-04-how-to-hire-a-twitter-army-like-the-guptas-did/&quot;&gt;The Times.&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Test" /><category term="Ipsum" /><category term="Markdown" /><category term="Portfolio" /><summary type="html">The Gupta family’s propaganda campaign, allegedly assisted by Bell Pottinger, inaugurated South Africa into the epicentre of the era of fake news and propaganda which has grown in tandem with the dominance of news by social media platforms. How does it work? A report by cybersecurity firm Trend Micro, “The Fake News Machine: How Propagandists Abuse the Internet and Manipulate the Public”, details how to set up or procure a group capable of employing “dark” means to amplify content online. These services are mostly found on the “darknet” (part of the internet infamous for the trade in illegal drugs, child porn and other illegal services). On the darknet, technology propagandists claim they can artificially manipulate a wide variety of online platforms including Facebook, Twitter, YouTube and Instagram. They offer services such as: On Twitter: creating accounts, buying followers and creating retweets; On Facebook: creating accounts, buying followers, comments and “likes”; On YouTube: buying “likes”, “dislikes”, views, video reviews and making videos appear on the front page; Using “click farms”, software and hardware for automating activities such as liking and following, and; News manipulation: for example, writing press releases and guaranteed article placements on news sites (especially in Russia and China). Trend Micro’s researchers identify distinct regions where prominent marketplaces exist, each with their own culture, tools and platform priorities. These are China, the Middle East, India and English-speaking communities. The Russian community has a particular focus on using real humans to complete tasks through crowdsourcing platforms. Some of these darknet platforms to manipulate social media are very large. Vtope reportedly has two million “mostly real” users and SMOFast has roughly 500,000 registered users. There is evidence that suggests that India, along with Bell Pottinger in the UK, were part of a multinational campaign of fake news sponsored by the Gupta family. Internet sleuth Jean le Roux has followed the bot army for months. He first revealed its existence in the Daily Maverick when he showed how a sample of fake accounts was spreading the propaganda at exactly the same time, which indicated an automated campaign. In other words, the accounts did not act as individual humans but as a trolling battalion acting for a political purpose. “It’s definitely multinational,” says Le Roux, who would send some of the accounts links. When those behind the accounts opened the links, it revealed to Le Roux that the accounts were generated from both South Africa and India. The campaigners used rupee (the Indian currency) to use Google Ads or promoted tweets to increase the visibility of their messages. Some of the fake accounts were linked to documents that were often geo-located in India. In other words, the Gupta family’s Twitter army left a digital footprint. In addition, says Le Roux, his suspicions were piqued when the accounts carried names like Bongi Vorster and Dlamini Louw. While African-Afrikaans name and surname combinations are known, they are rare — but were very common in the fake army. “It was as if someone had been given a spreadsheet of South African names and surnames which were then automatically generating combinations,” he says. Then Le Roux sent the fake accounts messages in several South African languages other than English, and they couldn’t answer. All this indicated a paid foreign army with its base probably in India. While there is no direct evidence of Bell Pottinger’s role in this part of the campaign, the company has a long history of propaganda black operations. These “black ops” hide the creators of work that is designed to confuse and destabilise countries. The PR company has most recently been exposed for its work in Iraq where it created videos and other material to smoke out alleged Al-Qaeda operatives. Wikipedia founder Jimmy Wales banned Bell Pottinger from editing on the open online encyclopaedia after it was found to have manipulated various entries. The Bell Pottinger team that worked on South Africa also sanitised the Gupta family’s Wikipedia entry, as The Times has previously shown. This story was published in partnership with The Times.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/img/blog/Thumb-3.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Story 2</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story_2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Story 2" /><published>2017-12-10T00:00:00+06:00</published><updated>2017-12-10T00:00:00+06:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story_2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story_2.html">&lt;p&gt;
          Bell Pottinger was introduced into the Gupta corporate empire by an associate of the family, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/sunday-times/news/2016-04-03-arms-deal-man-took-jonas-to-meet-guptas/&quot;&gt;Fana Hlongwane&lt;/a&gt;, who got to know the public relations company as he battled against exposés made against him during the arms deal.
          Hlongwane, who has been fingered as the middleman between the South African government and UK arms supplier BAE Systems, is widely regarded as the biggest beneficiary of “commissions” in the arms deal in the early 2000s.
          He was introduced to Bell Pottinger by the father of Victoria Geoghegan, who was promoted to vice-president in December 2016. She has since been fired as the company attempted to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/sunday-times/opinion-and-analysis/2017-08-02-fact-vs-fiction-how-bell-pottinger-and-atul-gupta-spun-the-bbc/&quot;&gt;limit damage to its reputation&lt;/a&gt;. It has had to face an unprecedented inquiry before the PR regulatory body in the UK after a complaint by the DA.
          The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/politics/2017-08-21-guptaemails-the-mystery-of-the-great-dubai-gathering/&quot;&gt;Gupta patrons and their political players&lt;/a&gt; began the campaign when their effort to install Des van Rooyen as finance minister in December 2015 backfired spectacularly.
          They needed a new plan — and the chronology of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/group/Gupta_Emails_Revealed/&quot;&gt;#GuptaEmails&lt;/a&gt; reveals how Bell Pottinger helped to package the new message.
          Shortly after the narrative targeting white monopoly capital was bedded down, the fake-news enterprise sprang to life early in 2016.
          The disinformation campaign used a range of media to carry the propaganda: the New Age newspaper and TV channel ANN7; alternative news sites Black Opinion, Uncensored and Weekly Exposé; pro-Gupta websites AtulGupta.com and TruthbyConnorMead.co.za; and websites and blogs such as WMCLeaks, WMCScams, Dodgy SA Ministers, and Voetsek.
          The propaganda campaign is evolving constantly. What draws all the elements together?
          Investigations by Scorpio and AmaBhungane have revealed that several of the sites were created or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dailymaverick.co.za/article/2017-06-22-scorpio-in-the-non-surprise-of-the-year-wmcleaks.com-smear-campaign-tracked-to-a-gupta-associate/&quot;&gt;linked to the same Gupta employee&lt;/a&gt;, Himanshu Tanwar, via his company FutureTeq.
          Our  investigation also reveals the following similarities:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;     

  &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;They are all promoted by the same fake accounts on Twitter and pages on Facebook;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;They use similar Wordpress templates and layouts;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;They share content through re-blogs and syndication;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;All the website “owners” are regular analysts on ANN7, and;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;They share website developers and creators.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;/ul&gt;
          
          The &lt;a href=&quot;https://mg.co.za/article/2016-11-23-00-time-to-cause-some-havoc-the-weird-web-of-gupta-linked-misinformation&quot;&gt;Mail &amp;amp; Guardian has reported&lt;/a&gt;, for example, that the Voetsek blog and TruthbyConnormead.co.za use the same e-mail service, software and service provider.
          In addition, a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.news24.com/SouthAfrica/News/exclusive-indian-it-guru-linked-to-fake-wmc-sites-20170726&quot;&gt;News24 investigation&lt;/a&gt; revealed that Kapil Garg, the creator and owner of the most recent WMC Leaks campaign, has several possible links to the Guptas. WMC Leaks emerged as a direct response to the leak of e-mails which have revealed the extent of state capture by the Gupta family.

          This story was published in partnership with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/news/south-africa/2017-09-04-how-the-guptas-propaganda-war-machine-was-built/&quot;&gt;The Times.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Test" /><category term="Ipsum" /><category term="Markdown" /><category term="Portfolio" /><summary type="html">Bell Pottinger was introduced into the Gupta corporate empire by an associate of the family, Fana Hlongwane, who got to know the public relations company as he battled against exposés made against him during the arms deal. Hlongwane, who has been fingered as the middleman between the South African government and UK arms supplier BAE Systems, is widely regarded as the biggest beneficiary of “commissions” in the arms deal in the early 2000s. He was introduced to Bell Pottinger by the father of Victoria Geoghegan, who was promoted to vice-president in December 2016. She has since been fired as the company attempted to limit damage to its reputation. It has had to face an unprecedented inquiry before the PR regulatory body in the UK after a complaint by the DA. The Gupta patrons and their political players began the campaign when their effort to install Des van Rooyen as finance minister in December 2015 backfired spectacularly. They needed a new plan — and the chronology of the #GuptaEmails reveals how Bell Pottinger helped to package the new message. Shortly after the narrative targeting white monopoly capital was bedded down, the fake-news enterprise sprang to life early in 2016. The disinformation campaign used a range of media to carry the propaganda: the New Age newspaper and TV channel ANN7; alternative news sites Black Opinion, Uncensored and Weekly Exposé; pro-Gupta websites AtulGupta.com and TruthbyConnorMead.co.za; and websites and blogs such as WMCLeaks, WMCScams, Dodgy SA Ministers, and Voetsek. The propaganda campaign is evolving constantly. What draws all the elements together? Investigations by Scorpio and AmaBhungane have revealed that several of the sites were created or linked to the same Gupta employee, Himanshu Tanwar, via his company FutureTeq. Our investigation also reveals the following similarities:</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/img/blog/Thumb-0.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Story 1</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Story 1" /><published>2017-12-10T00:00:00+06:00</published><updated>2017-12-10T00:00:00+06:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/2017/12/10/Main-Story.html">&lt;p&gt;UK PR firm Bell Pottinger’s role in the construction of the Gupta family’s propaganda empire was part of a multinational fake news scheme to hide the family’s growing enrichment at the expense of South African citizens and taxpayers. 
The Times, with the African Network of Centres for Investigative Reporting, for the first time reveals the size and scope of a campaign which outpaces the apartheid-era Information Scandal in cost and political impact. 
Bell Pottinger is facing a severe backlash as a result of its role. 
On Monday, the Public Relations and Communication Association in the UK was due to meet to consider the company’s appeal against an adverse finding which the association has made against it. The final decision was due on Tuesday and Bell Pottinger’s future could hang on its outcome. 
This investigation reveals a multi-channel media empire that includes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/sunday-times/news/2017-08-26-i-know-what-ive-signed-up-for-manyi-spills-the-beans-on-his-new-business/&quot;&gt;mainstream news outlets The New Age and ANN7&lt;/a&gt;, alternative news websites, and a vast number of contributors to social media including Twitter, Facebook and Instagram.&lt;br /&gt;
It is the first large-scale fake news propaganda war in South Africa, and it has adversely affected the country’s politics and economy.&lt;br /&gt;
This network of fake news produced at least 220,000 tweets and hundreds of Facebook posts to confuse the public between July 2016 and July 2017, when this report’s remit stopped. Since then the pace has picked up.&lt;br /&gt;
The largest period of sustained activity was spent attacking &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/sunday-times/opinion-and-analysis/2017-08-31-why-gordhan-and-not-the-guptas-might-be-in-the-dock-soon/&quot;&gt;former finance minister Pravin Gordhan&lt;/a&gt; in the second half of 2016 to create a climate conducive to forcing his removal as finance minister.&lt;br /&gt;
Now the network has entered a new phase of heightened activity and has sharpened its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/politics/2017-08-16-he-is-no-wife-beater-dirty-tricks-are-being-used-against-ramaphosa-voices-mount-in-support-of-deputy-president/&quot;&gt;attacks on Deputy President Cyril Ramaphosa&lt;/a&gt; and his race for the ANC presidency.&lt;br /&gt;
Over the weekend, Ramaphosa was forced to defend himself in the face of private emails which had been apparently hacked and leaked to the Sunday Independent and which claimed he has had a string of extra-marital affairs.&lt;br /&gt;
The distribution of the latest accusations against Rampahosa this weekend followed a similar pattern to other propaganda conclusively linked to the fake news network.&lt;br /&gt;
The fake news network has started a separate and well-funded campaign to respond to the tranche of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/group/Gupta_Emails_Revealed/&quot;&gt;#GuptaEmails&lt;/a&gt; in the form of #WMCLeaks, which features websites as well as social feeds that spew out a daily range of propaganda. Analysts say it would require a full-time army of IT technologists, writers, editors and graphic artists to produce a volume of material like this.&lt;br /&gt;
Our reports will take you into the dark heart of a propaganda assault which is shaping the South African story.&lt;br /&gt;
This weekend, Bell Pottinger chief executive and major shareholder James Henderson resigned. In July, he had issued an “unequivocal” apology for the campaign.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What was the Information Scandal?&lt;/strong&gt; 
The Information Scandal, or Muldergate, of the 1970s is the name given to an explosive exposé of how the apartheid state raided the fiscus to run a propaganda campaign which included funding the Citizen newspaper. It involved placing propaganda in international media to gloss its image, which was growing murkier as the anti-apartheid movement gained ground.&lt;br /&gt;
The name was coined for then information minister Connie Mulder whose secretary, Eschel Rhoodie, masterminded the campaign to divert funds from a defence project to fund the disinformation campaign.&lt;br /&gt;
When the Rand Daily Mail and the Sunday Express, leading titles of the time, broke the story, all hell broke loose. &lt;br /&gt;
Investigations were held and both Mulder and Rhoodie lost their jobs. Prime minister John Vorster fell and PW Botha came to office on the back of the scandal. 
The second Information Scandal is more powerful as it rides on the back of a digital explosion that enables fake news (or propaganda) to travel more widely, cheaply and lethally. 
Other elements, which circle the similarities, are the diversion of state funds to enable it. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/group/Gupta_Emails_Revealed/&quot;&gt;#GuptaEmails&lt;/a&gt;, as well as reports into state capture, show that the Gupta family’s business empire was enabled by diverting funds from the government and state-owned enterprises. Both the New Age newspaper and the television station ANN7 are heavily reliant on government advertising. 
The purpose of the second Information Scandal is similar to the first — to shield a malignant political order that faces national opprobrium.&lt;br /&gt;
This story was originally published in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeslive.co.za/news/south-africa/2017-09-04-the-guptas-bell-pottinger-and-the-fake-news-propaganda-machine/&quot;&gt;The Times.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Test" /><category term="Ipsum" /><category term="Markdown" /><category term="Portfolio" /><summary type="html">UK PR firm Bell Pottinger’s role in the construction of the Gupta family’s propaganda empire was part of a multinational fake news scheme to hide the family’s growing enrichment at the expense of South African citizens and taxpayers. The Times, with the African Network of Centres for Investigative Reporting, for the first time reveals the size and scope of a campaign which outpaces the apartheid-era Information Scandal in cost and political impact. Bell Pottinger is facing a severe backlash as a result of its role. On Monday, the Public Relations and Communication Association in the UK was due to meet to consider the company’s appeal against an adverse finding which the association has made against it. The final decision was due on Tuesday and Bell Pottinger’s future could hang on its outcome. This investigation reveals a multi-channel media empire that includes mainstream news outlets The New Age and ANN7, alternative news websites, and a vast number of contributors to social media including Twitter, Facebook and Instagram. It is the first large-scale fake news propaganda war in South Africa, and it has adversely affected the country’s politics and economy. This network of fake news produced at least 220,000 tweets and hundreds of Facebook posts to confuse the public between July 2016 and July 2017, when this report’s remit stopped. Since then the pace has picked up. The largest period of sustained activity was spent attacking former finance minister Pravin Gordhan in the second half of 2016 to create a climate conducive to forcing his removal as finance minister. Now the network has entered a new phase of heightened activity and has sharpened its attacks on Deputy President Cyril Ramaphosa and his race for the ANC presidency. Over the weekend, Ramaphosa was forced to defend himself in the face of private emails which had been apparently hacked and leaked to the Sunday Independent and which claimed he has had a string of extra-marital affairs. The distribution of the latest accusations against Rampahosa this weekend followed a similar pattern to other propaganda conclusively linked to the fake news network. The fake news network has started a separate and well-funded campaign to respond to the tranche of #GuptaEmails in the form of #WMCLeaks, which features websites as well as social feeds that spew out a daily range of propaganda. Analysts say it would require a full-time army of IT technologists, writers, editors and graphic artists to produce a volume of material like this. Our reports will take you into the dark heart of a propaganda assault which is shaping the South African story. This weekend, Bell Pottinger chief executive and major shareholder James Henderson resigned. In July, he had issued an “unequivocal” apology for the campaign. What was the Information Scandal? The Information Scandal, or Muldergate, of the 1970s is the name given to an explosive exposé of how the apartheid state raided the fiscus to run a propaganda campaign which included funding the Citizen newspaper. It involved placing propaganda in international media to gloss its image, which was growing murkier as the anti-apartheid movement gained ground. The name was coined for then information minister Connie Mulder whose secretary, Eschel Rhoodie, masterminded the campaign to divert funds from a defence project to fund the disinformation campaign. When the Rand Daily Mail and the Sunday Express, leading titles of the time, broke the story, all hell broke loose. Investigations were held and both Mulder and Rhoodie lost their jobs. Prime minister John Vorster fell and PW Botha came to office on the back of the scandal. The second Information Scandal is more powerful as it rides on the back of a digital explosion that enables fake news (or propaganda) to travel more widely, cheaply and lethally. Other elements, which circle the similarities, are the diversion of state funds to enable it. The #GuptaEmails, as well as reports into state capture, show that the Gupta family’s business empire was enabled by diverting funds from the government and state-owned enterprises. Both the New Age newspaper and the television station ANN7 are heavily reliant on government advertising. The purpose of the second Information Scandal is similar to the first — to shield a malignant political order that faces national opprobrium. This story was originally published in The Times.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://0.0.0.0:4000/img/blog/Thumb-2.jpg" /></entry></feed>